Game playing.
There's been a lot of advances in
game playing. I'm going to tell you a lot about
the classic thing because I think
actually this is one of these pivotal
points in AI where we kind of
really realize that maybe we have capacities that we didn't before.
Before we could play checkers. Today,
checkers is solved.
We'll talk more about checkers when we talk about game-playing later,
but there was this classic moment in May
of 1997. Deep Blue, which is shown here--
Deep Blue looks approximately like a
refrigerator, is giant, parallel,
special-purpose hardware
that basically exists to crunch through
chess positions
and it beat the world champion Kasparov,
and the sequence of moves
was described as intelligent and
creative, as opposed to kinda maybe alien
and weird. You could imagine humans being,
like, well, that's, yeah I guess that those
moves are legal but weird right. You can
imagine, you kind of play chess and
all the pieces scatter to the corner and
they come back and you've lost and you're like
what the heck just happened.
But no it's just like, yeah, that's a
good move, you know. That's better than the human.
And you can interpret it,
and that's amazing!
This thing's crunching two hundred million
board positions per second. It was amazing then.
You can now do that with a PC
cluster so things have advanced obviously.
But the amazing thing is, it's doing
nothing like with the humans are doing
when they play chess. But the resulting
behavior is surprisingly similar, and
this is a case of there are a lot of
different computations you can do, but
there is good kind of rational
behavior and multiple ways to get
there. We don't always know how humans get there.
But we do have ways of making machines
do it in some way.
So, there's this open question: How do humans play chess?
There's lots of things you just can't do. When you get into like a multiplication race with the computer,
like here's some five digit numbers, go!
Like you know you're going to lose.
There's just things where you know the computer is better.
Why isn't the computer just so much better at chess that we lost this
battle in the eighties? It's an open
question how humans are so good. I mean,
they lose, but it's like, they try,
its kinda amazing how humans
can compete with computers at all.
Okay, in 1996 actually,
Kasparov beat Deep Blue and had some
really nice words to say. Kasparov said,
"I could feel--I could smell--a new kind
of intelligence across the table".
I don't really know what that
means like some new
intelligence scent you can hang in your car,
but Kasparov is very positive. And then in
1997,
"Deep Blue hasn't proven anything."
So...
yeah, I guess that's more a comment about humans.
There have been huge advances in game playing recently. For example, in Go.
A couple of years ago when I would talk
about Go I would say, Go is a case where
humans are so much better than machines,
that the human masters will not even play the
machines because it's insulting.
Now the machines are pretty good, and able
to play extremely competitive people,
and win.
and that's been very recent. We'll talk about how some of those advances work much later.